James G. Harbord Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
James G. Harbord Papers 1886-1938 (bulk 1917-1919)
MSS24844
Harbord, James G. (James Guthrie), 1866-1947
24,000 items
38 containers
14 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Army officer and business executive. Correspondence, personal diary, confidential cables, administrative memoranda of General John J. Pershing, records of conversations, clippings, scrapbooks, operational maps, barrage charts, sketches, records of the United States Army 2nd Division, a portrait, translations of war diaries of the German army, and other papers pertaining to Harbord's service in the American military, principally during World War I.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937--Correspondence.; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937.; Bandholtz, Harry Hill, 1864-1925--Correspondence.; Bliss, Tasker Howard, 1853-1930--Correspondence.; Degoutte, Jean, 1866-1938--Correspondence.; Haig, Douglas Haig, Earl, 1861-1928--Correspondence.; Harbord, James G. (James Guthrie), 1866-1947.; Harts, W. W. (William Wright), 1866-1961--Correspondence.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964--Correspondence.; Johnson, Hugh S. (Hugh Samuel), 1882-1942--Correspondence.; March, Peyton Conway, 1864-1955--Correspondence.; McCoy, Frank Ross, 1874-1954--Correspondence.; McIntyre, Frank, 1865-1944--Correspondence.; Palmer, John McAuley, 1870-1955--Correspondence.; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948--Correspondence.; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948.; Pétain, Philippe, 1856-1951--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919--Correspondence.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930--Correspondence.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927--Correspondence.
Organizations
Germany Heer.; Philippine Constabulary.; United States. American Military Mission to Armenia, 1919.; United States. Army--Supplies and stores.; United States. Army.; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces. Services of Supply.; United States. Army. Division, 2nd.; United States. Army. Division, 2nd. United States Army 2nd Division records.
Subjects
Château-Thierry, Battle of, Château-Thierry, France, 1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--France.; World War, 1914-1918.
Places
Armenia--History--Revolution, 1917-1920.; Soissons (France)--History.
Occupations
Army officers.; Executives.
Provenance
The papers of James G. Harbord, army officer and business executive, were given to the Library of Congress by Harbord in 1945. An earlier gift had been received in 1923.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of James G. Harbord are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of James Guthrie Harbord (1866-1947) span the years 1886-1938, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1917-1919. The collection consists of correspondence, personal diary, confidential cables, administrative memoranda of General John J. Pershing, records of conversations, clippings, scrapbooks, operational maps, barrage charts, sketches, a portrait, records of the United States Army 2nd Division, a portrait, translations of war diaries of the German army, and other papers pertaining to Harbord's career in the United States Army. Featured are Harbord’s service as Pershing's chief of staff during World War I; as commander of a marine brigade during the battle of Chateau-Thierry, France, in 1918; commander of the 2nd Division in the Soissons offensive; and commander of the American Expeditionary Forces Service of Supply, 1918-1919. Also documented is Harbord’s service as chief of the American Military Mission to Armenia in 1919 as well as his postings prior to World War I, especially as assistant chief of the Philippine Constabulary. The papers are organized by topic or type of material.
Subjects include political and administrative issues within the military, Newton Diehl Baker's activities as secretary of war during World War I, and the relationship between Harbord and Baker until the latter’s death in 1938. Secretary Baker’s two visits to Europe, one during the war in 1918 and one in 1919 while the Peace Conference was in session at Paris, are briefly described, with accounts by Harbord on his conversations with the secretary. Contained in a volume of Harbord-Pershing correspondence are copies of Pershing’s administrative memoranda as well as Harbord’s own letters and communications. A volume of personal miscellany contains a note from J. C. Grew, enclosing to Harbord a ticket of admission to the Salle des Glaces in the Palace at Versailles, to witness the signing of the treaty of pace with Germany on June 28, 1919.
Correspondents in addition to Baker and Pershing include Harry Hill Bandholtz, Tasker Howard Bliss, Jean Degoutte, Earl Douglas Haig, W. W. Harts, Herbert Hoover, Hugh S. Johnson, Peyton Conway March, Frank Ross McCoy, Frank McIntyre, John McAuley Palmer, Philippe Pétain, Theodore Roosevelt, William H. Taft, and Leonard Wood.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Private letters, 1886-1916 (Box 1)
  Letters sent and received. Vol. 1 includes a typewritten diary of a trip by Harbord through parts of Russia and Europe, June 2, 1906- Sept. 8, 1906. The correspondence is arranged in chronologically. Included are letters from Leonard Wood, John J. Pershing, William H. Taft,and Frank McIntryre. The largest body of correspondence is with Harry Hill Bandholtz.
  - Vol. 1, 1886-1906 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 2, 1907-1908 (Box 2)
  - Vol. 3, 1909-1910 (Box 3)
  - Vol. 4, 1911-1912 (Box 4)
  - Vol. 5, 1913-1916 (Box 5)
- Military records, 1889-1916 (Box 6)
  Scrapbook containing newspaper and magazine clippings, original letters, commissions, certificates, orders, etc.
- World War I (Box 7)
  - Promotions and decorations, 1917-1919 (Box 7)
    Congratulatory letters and official notices on the promotions of Harbord. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Military activity (Box 8)
    - I, Official war activity (Box 8)
      - Introduction (Box 8)
      - Liberty Loan, 1917 (Box 8)
      - Military unification, Allied Services of Supply, 1918 (Box 8)
      - 2nd Division victory in Meaux District, 1918 (Box 8)
      - Cháteau-Thierry, Bouresches, and Bois de Belleau, 1918 (Box 8)
      - Harbord’s appeal for decorations for soldiers, 1918 (Box 8)
      - American Red Cross, 1919 (Box 8)
      - Services of Supply inspection tour, 1919 (Box 8)
      - Armenian Mission, 1919 (Box 8)
      - Retirement of Harbord, 1922 (Box 8)
    - II, Army correspondence, including letters, telegrams, orders, and memoranda, 1917-1921 (Box 8)
- Personal miscellany, 1917-1919 (Box 9)
  Scrapbook containing pictures, memoranda, menus, programs, invitations, etc.
- Personal war letters, 1917-1919 (Box 10)
  Preface, dated Dec. 1936, by Eleanor Kay Abrams. Included are letters or telegrams from Tasker Howard Bliss, John McAuley Palmer, John J. Pershing, and others. A typewritten copy of Newton Diehl Baker’s letter of Feb. 25, 1919 constitutes the introduction. Letters arranged alphabetically with index at the beginning.
- Pershing-Harbord letters, 1917-1922 (Box 11)
  Letters, telegrams, memoranda exchanged by John J. Pershing and Harboard. Harbord’s letters being for the most part in the form of carbon copies.
- Personal letters, Newton Diehl Baker, 1918-1938 (Box 12)
  Letters, telegrams, and related matter exchanged by Baker and Harbord. Harbord’s letters being for the most part in the form of typewritten copies signed. The last letter, Jan. 12, 1938, is from Mrs. Baker.
- American Expeditionary Forces (Box 13)
  - Confidential (Box 13)
    - Cables sent, July 2, 1917-Aug. 30, 1919 (Box 13)
      Six books of cables, bound as one volume. Largely from Pershing to adjutant general, War Department, or the adjutant general for the chief of staff, secretary of war, etc. (marked “3rd copy”)
    - Cables received, July 23, 1917-Aug. 30, 1919 (Box 14)
      Largely addressed to Pershing Amexforces (marked “3rd copy”) Five books of cables bound as one volume.
  - 2nd Division at Belleau Wood, 1918, June (Box 15)
    Carbon copies of orders sent by messenger, summaries of intelligence, resumes of activities, handwritten reports and memoranda, signed papers. Arranged in general chronological order with maps at the front of the volume. Includes General Order No. 1, June 6, 1919, mistakenly bound as part of this volume.
- Records of the 2nd Division [Regular], 1917-1918 (Box 16)
  Operation maps, barrage charts and sketches. Index at front.
- Translations of war diaries of German units opposed to the 2nd Division [Regular], 1918 (Box 17)
  Typewritten material. A foreword, June 20, 1930, bearing the heading “Second Division Historical Section, Army War College, Washington, D.C.,” signed by Captain C.O. Mattfeldt, explains the preparation and handling of the material in the volume. Includes a word of appreciation to the Deutsches Reicharchiv, Potsdam, Germany, for its courtesy in making available to the section the original war dairies of the German units that engaged the 2nd Division.
  - Vol. 1, Toulon-Troyon, Cháteau-Thierry (Box 17)
  - Vol. 2, Cháteau-Thierry (Box 18)
  - Vol. 3, Cháteau-Thierry (Box 19)
  - Vol. 4, Cháteau-Thierry (Box 20)
  - Vol. 5, Soissons (Box 21)
  - Vol. 6, Marbache, Saint-Mihiel (Box 22)
  - Vol. 7, Blanc Mont [Part I] (Box 23)
  - Vol. 8, Blanc Mont [Part II] (Box 24)
  - Vol. 9, Meuse-Argonne (Box 25)
- Records of the 2nd Division [Regular] (Box 26)
  Typewritten material “copied literally from original documents and most carefully compared,” according to a note at the front of vol. 1 by Brigadier General Preston Brown. This series was done under the direction of Captain C. O. Mattfeldt.
  - Vol. 1, 1918-1919, Field orders (Box 26)
  - Vol. 2, 1919-1919, Field orders (3rd and 4th Brigades) (Box 27)
  - Vol. 3, Field orders (9th Infantry-23rd Infantry, 5th Marines-6th Marines and 2nd Engineers) (Box 28)
  - Vol. 4, 1918, Field messages (Headquarters 2nd Division, 2nd Field Artillery Brigade, 3rd Brigade Marines) (Box 29)
  - Vol. 5, 1918, 9th-23rd Infantry, 5th- 6th Marines, 12th-15th and 17th Field Artillery, 2nd Engineers, 4th-5th-6th Machine Gun Battalions (Box 30)
  - Vol. 6, 1918, Operation Reports War Diaries Journal of Operations, (2nd Division, 2nd Field Artillery Brigade, 2nd Trench Mortar Battery, 3rd Brigade, 4th Brigade) (Box 31)
  - Vol. 7, 1918, Operations reports, war diaries, petrol reports (9th-23rd Infantry, 5th-6th Marines, 2nd Engineers) (Box 32)
  - Vol. 8, 1918, Operation reports, war diaries (12th-15th and 17th Field Artillery, 4th, 5th, and 6th Machine Gun Battalions, 1st Field Signal Battalion, 2nd Trains) (Box 33)
- Services of Supply (Box 34)
  Personal telegrams sent, 1918-1919. Carbon copies. Arranged chronologically.
  - Memoranda, 1919. Carbon copies. Arranged chronologically (Box 35)
- Clippings, 1917-1920, 1931 (Box 36)
- Scrapbook, circa 1923-1929 (Box 37)
  Pictures, clippings, menus, articles, etc. Pocket of loose material at the back of the volume.
- Maps showing operations of American divisions on Western Front (Box 38)
  Map room G-3, General Headquarters. Includes loose material consisting of maps, commissions, a portrait, a report, and a memorial of women of Armenia to Harbord, 1919.